Guide to Tuller House (Richfield Springs, NY) records, 1897-1920.
Fenimore Art Museum
Tuller House (Richfield Springs, N.Y.) records, 1897-1920.
The records in this collection document nearly every phase of operation of the Tuller House, Richfield Springs, New York. It consists of advertising copy; bills including those for goods, freight, power, and labor from scores of business establishments; broadsides; business cards and flyers; catalogs; cancelled checks; correspondence; employee applications and blank forms; employee rosters; inquiries from salesmen and prospective guests, entertainers, and employees; insurance documents; invoices; equipment manuals; newspaper copy; receipts including tax receipts; solicitations; statements; and telegrams.
1 cu. ft.
Tuller House (Richfield Springs, Otsego County, NY)
Fenimore Art Museum Research Library 80 Lake Road Cooperstown, NY 13326
Coll. No. 446
Related Material
Coll. No. 307 Hotel Club correspondence, 1925-1926.
Purchase; Steve Resnick, Cazenovia, N.Y.; 2003; NM-24.2001
Acquisition Information
Coll. No. 446 is open for research according to the regulations of Fenimore Art Museum Library.
Tuller House, located on Main Street, was one of the popular hotels when Richfield Springs was a prominent health and pleasure resort. Over time the hotel was also known as The Tuller House, The Tuller, Bloomfield’s, Hotel Bloomfield, and The Bloomfield. As early as 1874, N. J. Jewell was advertised as its owner and proprietor and in 1882 his hotel, open from June – October with a capacity of 100 guests, was enlarged and re-furnished. These records show that in 1900, The Tuller was owned by N. D. Jewell and Company and managed by H. H. Tuller. Henry H. Tuller and/or Mrs. Henry H. Tuller were owner(s) and manager(s) after ca. 1900- 1906. Allen J. Bloomfield became involved in the Tuller House from 1907, is listed as manager in 1912, and proprietor in 1913. In 1915 the name of the hotel was “Bloomfields” and Mr. Bloomfield continued as proprietor at least until the end of the collection’s datespan, 1920.
Biography/History
Bloomfield, Allen J.; Jewel, N. J.; Tuller, Henry H.; Tuller, Mrs. Henry H.; N. D. Jewell and Company; Advertising--Hotels--New York (State); Hotel management.; Hotels--Accounting--New York (State); Hotels--Employees.; Hotels--New York (State) Richfield Springs.; Richfield Springs (N.Y.)--Business, industries, and trades--Hotels, taverns, etc.; Tuller Hotel (Richfield Springs, N.Y.); Richfield Springs (Otsego County, N.Y.); account books; Broadsides (notices); Checks (bank checks); Commercial catalogs; correspondence; Flyers (printed matter); Invoices (financial records); Photographs; Receipts (financial records); rosters; School notebooks
The records in this collection document nearly every phase of operation of the Tuller House, Richfield Springs, New York. It consists of advertising copy; bills including those for goods, freight, power, and labor from scores of business establishments; broadsides; business cards and flyers; catalogs; cancelled checks; correspondence; employee applications and blank forms; employee rosters; inquiries from salesmen and prospective guests, entertainers, and employees; insurance documents; invoices; equipment manuals; newspaper copy; receipts including tax receipts; solicitations; statements; and telegrams.
Scope and Contents
Among the correspondence are letters written by Thomas Redfield Proctor, Caroline Kernan, and John Butler of Utica, NY. Additionally, there are four menus from The Tuller (1904 and 1909) and The Five-Mile Point Inn (1909), and three newspapers: the Lakewood Item, 3/20/1912; Mail and Express, 4/19/1902; and a scrap of Richfield Daily, July 1895.
Also included are a “Report on Gathering of Historical Data from ‘The Tuller,’ Richfield Springs, NY” (1953), a copy of the Sales Agreement for the lumber from the hotel (1953) and three b&w photos of the hotel taken prior to and during its demolishing (1952-1953).
The eight account books (1890-1895, 1900-1901, 1904, 1912, undated) document monies paid for hotel operations to businesses and individuals; "servants" and their names, dates hired, and wages; general and personal expenses; expenses for help, entertainment, house repairs, and liquor; and monies paid for “bus and baggage,” hotel supplies, and groceries. The Tuller House checkbook (1906-1907) documents checks written to individuals, businesses, and cash. Tuller House Time Book lists employee names and hours for the 1901 season. And M. Tuller and Son Department Store receipts (1913-1914) document purchases of various grocery items, mostly fruit, vegetables, poultry, and dairy products in large quantities, probably for hotel operations.
Also included are student notebooks created by Allen Bloomfield (3) and H. H. Tuller (1) and two 6”x6” green ceramic fireplace tiles which were removed from the Tuller House barroom in 1953.
- 446.1/1 Tuller House Collection, Scope + Content and Provenance notes., u.d.
- 446.1/2 Bloomfield, Allen J., student notebooks., 1901 - 1903
- 446.1/3 Booklet, "Tucker's Method of Turf Production"., 1914
- 446.1/4 M. Tuller and Son Department Store, receipts. (1 of 2), 1913 - 1914
- 446.1/5 M. Tuller and Son Department Store, receipts. (2 of 2), 1913 - 1914
- 446.1/6 Tuller House, Account book., 1901
- 446.1/7 Tuller House, Account book., 1901 - 1903
- 446.1/8 Tuller House, Account book., 1902
- 446.1/9 Tuller House, Account book., 1905
- 446.1/10 Tuller House, Account book., u.d.
- 446.1/11 Tuller House, Account books, bus and baggage., 1889, 1891.
- 446.1/12 Tuller House, Account books, grocery purchases., 1890 - 1912
- 446.1/13 Tuller House, Account book, guests., 1906 - 1907
- 446.1/13a Tuller House, Acount book, help., 1906 - 1907
- 446.1/14 Tuller House, Checkbook [stubs only]., 1906 - 1907
- 446.1/15 Tuller House, File Box #1, cancelled checks and receipts., 1897 - 1915
- 446.1/16 Tuller House, File Box #1, A-D., 1901 - 1915
- 446.1/17 Tuller House, File Box #1, E/F-G., 1903 - 1920
- 446.1/18 Tuller House, File Box #1, H-R., 1900 - 1915
- 446.1/19 Tuller House, File box #1, S-Z., 1900 - 1914
- 446.1/20 Tuller House, File Box #1, Correspondence, unalphabetized., 1902 - 1913
- 446.1/21 Tuller House, File Box #2, A-E/F, 1900 - 1915
- 446.1/22 Tuller House, File Box #2, G-R., 1900
- 446.1/23 Tuller House, File box #2, S-Z.
- 446.1/24 Tuller House, Fireplace tiles., u.d.
- 446.1/25 Tuller House, Misc. documents., u.d.
- 446.1/26 Tuller House, Receipts., 1904
- 446.1/27 Tuller House, Time book., 1901
- 446.1/28 Tuller, H. H., Notebook, metalurgy., u.d.